A Guide to the Hamlin/Mitchell Family Papers 1885-1960
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
The Hamlin/Mitchell Family Papers 1885-1960
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1979-11
37 items
The Hamlin/Mitchell Family
Administrative Information
Access
No restrictions on access.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Hamlin Family of Petersburg were members of a large antibellum free black community. At the conclusion of the civil war, The hamlin's became active in city politics and were quite involved in emerging African American Middle class.
One member of this family William Hamlin, A graduate of Hampton Institute became the first African American principal of a school in Petersburg. Hamlin later became Principal of Peabody. In addition, Mr. Hamlin was one of the corp of teachers selected to teach in the summer institute for "Colored" teachers sponsored by both the Peabody Reading Circle and the State of Virginia.
A number of individuals from this family were quite active during the era of Reconstruction and the Readjuster movement in Virginia. According to family history, members of the family, Cornelius Hamlin was assistant to the mayor of Petersburg. Edward Hamlin was clerk of the Court. According to family history, James Edward Hamlin was also associated with the Underground Railroad in Petersburg. A number of people from this family were associated with education. Sarah T. Byrd was one of the first African American teachers hired in the city.
Scope and Content Information
The Hamlin/Mitchell papers do contain a few letters most of which are related to Williams Hamlin activities with the Peabody Reading Circle.Other correspondence in the group was generated by Miss Wilhelimina Hamlin.Most of Miss Hamlin's correspondence document's her long career in education. Other documents found are circulars, invitations, and broadsides.
Series Description
Series I. Legal Indenture 1887
Series II. Correspondence Business correspondence, most of which concern educational matters.
Series III. Printed Circulars, Invitation, Flyers, Brochures, and programs
Series IV. Photographs A number of photograph documenting articles at Gillfield Baptist. There are several photographs of students and activities at the Motoaca Laboratory School located on the Campus of Virginia State University.
Series V. Literary A group of poems and other writings by William Hamlin.
Contents List
- Series I: Legal Documents
  - Legal documents, Agreement Aug. 1887 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence/Postcards 1885 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence 1886 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence 1887 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence 1888-1889 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence 1891 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence/Postcards 1899 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence 1928,1949-1953 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence 1956,1973 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence- Graduate School 1947,1949 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence- meeting V.T.A. 1947,1953 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence- T.V. Programs, American ED week 1956 (Folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence- Retirement 1950 (Folder 1:14)
- Series III: Printed
  - Circular-Harrison Street 1904 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Constitution- Young Ladies Social Club, Pilg, Va. 1893 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Invitation- Knickerbockers- Athlete Association (Folder 1:17)
  - Flyer- Oak Street A.M.E.Z. Church 1897 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Supervising Bulletin 1940 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Workshop School Principals 1953 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Awards 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Awards 1959 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Certificate-Petersburg Normal 1882 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Certificate- Staunton Normal 1883 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Certificate Department of Public Institution 1915 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Certificate- State Board of Education 1941 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Speech- Thank You Peabody 1887 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Political- Working means Union Republican Party Political- Election Ticket (A.W. Harris) 1871,1887 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Broadside- Republican Appeal- Frederick Douglas 1887 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Broadside- To The voter of Petersburg 1887 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Broadside- A.P. Hill, Confederate Veteran (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Report- Christian School Relation Committee, St. Stephens Church 1958 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - The Parish Bulliten, St. Stephens Church 1955 (Box-folder 1:33)
- Series III: Printed
  - Collected Programs 1948-1957 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Programs (V.N. & C.I. - V.S.C.) 1884-1964 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - News Clippings 1882 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Program (peabody Alumni Shields) 1944 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Unidentified Family n.d. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Gillsfield Baptist Church Group n.d. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Gillsfield Baptist Church Group n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Gillsfield Baptist Church Group n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Gillsfield Baptist Church Group n.d. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - n.d. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - The Jones Street School n.d. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Photographs V.S.U. Workshops n.d. (Box-folder 2:12)
- Series V. Scrapbook
  - Poems by W.L. Hamlin n.d. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Newspaper Clippings n.d. (Box-folder 3:2)